בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ב, Pey-Bet, 82. We're
going to wrap up one פרק perek and begin another one, and
the we had been saying that the משנה, mishna, which spoke about
somebody who gave money to a storekeeper to buy some, to buy
some bread for the עירוב, eiruv, he should have a portion in
the bread because technically he didn't take possession of it. He gave
the money but he didn't take possession, he doesn't own the bread.
And then even if that bread is used by another for an
עירוב, eiruv, it doesn't work for him because he only wanted to
do it through purchase, he didn't want to do it through somebody
giving it to him. And that seems like a very technical reason.
I mean, clearly he wanted to do an עירוב, eiruv, but nevertheless,
because it wasn't the way exactly the way he wanted, it doesn't
work. To that, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda voiced an opposition and, or
whatever, a clarification, and רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda said that's only by
עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumin, because עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin is an, is
something that is you really have to personally want to do, because
if you whatever you gain on one side you lose on the
other side. So there it has to be exactly according to the
person's wishes and exactly the way the person has sort of set
it up, even if interestingly broad strokes he's indicated he wants to
do it, but nevertheless, that's עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin. עירוב חצרות, eiruv
chatzeiros, however, is only to the person's benefit and therefore you, it
does not have to be לדעתו. l'da'ato. Okay, so that is very
reasonable, that we've sort of been saying, and then the גמרא gemara
just ended with discussing whether there's anybody that argues on רבי יהודה
Rabi Yehuda and says that עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros would require also
him being made aware about things like this and being brought in
and being done לדעתו. l'da'ato. As we pointed out also yesterday, it's
hard to see why anybody would argue with רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda
if you are using your own food. I'm going to be מזכה
mezakeh my food to you, it's only a gain for you, it's
not a loss, why would anybody think it would have to be
לדעתו? l'da'ato? And therefore based on previous גמרות, gemaras, it makes sense
to think that maybe the issue is more when it's your food
that's at stake. Can I take your food for your sake for
עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros or not? So that anyway is the position
of רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. The גמרא gemara has a question whether
anybody disagrees with it. Either way, we rule like רבי יהודה Rabi
Yehuda that עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros is a זכות zechus and therefore
can be done even שלא לדעת shelo l'da'as of the person, but
again, not clear whether it's even with using his food or only
with using your food. Okay, now the גמרא gemara picks up where
we asked, like, you know, don't worry about which way you put
it for my עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumin, I'm okay.
Yeah, then that's לדעתו. l'da'ato. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara two
lines from the top continues with this, because in that discussion it
was questioning whether there was a debate with רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda
or whether he was just clarifying, and it had the statement that
when רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says certain words in a משנה, mishna,
he's not debating, he's clarifying. So we pick up with that גופא,
gufa, two lines from the top.
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: Amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi: כל מקום
שאמר רבי יהודה אימתי ובמה, Kol makom she'amar Rabi Yehuda Eimasai u-vameh,
whenever he says אימתי eimasai or under, you know, when or under
what circumstances, במשנה, be-mishna, in a משנה, mishna, אינו אלא לפרש דברי
חכמים. eino ela le-fareish divrei chachamim. He's only clarifying what the חכמים
chachamim said, he's not really arguing with them.
ורבי יוחנן אמר: Ve-Rabi Yochanan amar: אימתי לפרש ובמה לחלוק. eimasai le-fareish
u-vameh lachlok. אימתי Eimasai means when is this true, that's clarifying,
ובמה, u-vameh, under what, which is a similar word, in what cases,
that's לחלוק. lachlok. That means he's actually disagreeing. He says no, no,
no, only in case A, not in case B. Okay, so one
case, one point is clarifying. Both of them are qualifying it, limiting
it to certain cases, but one is arguing and the other is
clarifying. So the גמרא gemara says ואימתי לפרש, ve-eimasai le-fareish, is it
true that אימתי eimasai is to clarify? Both opinions agree that אימתי
eimasai means to clarify. והתנן: Ve-ha tnan: ואלו הן הפסולין, ve-eilu hein
ha-psulin, these following people are invalid to testify: המשחק בקוביא, ha-mesachek be-kubya,
somebody who plays with dice, a gambler, והמלווה בריבית, ve-ha-malveh be-ribis, or
somebody who lends with ריבית, ribis, interest, ומפריחי יונים, u-mafrichay yonim, and
somebody who chases pigeons,
another type of a gambler, וסוחרי שביעית, ve-socheirei shevi'is, and people that
sell שביעית shevi'is produce. Okay, so what's the reason? So presumably all
of these are because they have improper monetary gains, and if you're
willing to violate in order to, in order to make money, then
maybe you'll testify falsely in order to make money. So therefore you're
חשוד, kashud, you're suspect because of what you will do for money.
אמר רבי יהודה: Amar Rabi Yehuda: אימתי, eimasai, so רבי יהודה Rabi
Yehuda says when is this true, presumably referring to the gambler cases,
המשחק בקוביא ha-mesachek be-kubya and המפריח יונים. ha-mafriach yonim. When is this
true? בזמן שאין לו אומנות אלא היא, be-zman she-ein lo umnus ela
hi, when this is their only profession. אבל יש לו אומנות שלא
היא, aval yesh lo umnus she-lo hi, if they have another profession,
הרי זה כשר, harei zeh kasher, then they are כשר. kasher. Now
this פשט pshat is discussing the gambler case because this is the
debate the גמרא gemara says whether אסמכתא קניא, asmachta kanya, whether gambling
really is a legitimate קנין, kinyan, right? If I say, you know,
we put money down and we say the person whose, I don't
know, pigeon crosses the line first or whatever wins it, so maybe
that should be a binding contract, you know, is it a binding
contract or not? And the question, there's two issues. One is that
you need some type of a קנין kinyan to make it
effective, like. like maybe we do a קניין סודר kinyan sudar or
something, you know, normally you need some formal act to make something
binding. But even if you've done that formal act,
you know, nobody really goes into it. The גמרא's Gemara point is
that why's אסמכתא לא קניא? asmachta lo kanya? אסמכתא Asmachta means that
it's sort of something that's done on an expectation but which won't
necessarily happen. Because when you enter into a bet, it's only because
you assume you're going to win. So you never really were committing
to pay deep down in case you were going to lose because
you never really assumed you were going to lose.
And therefore that's the debate whether אסמכתא קניא. asmachta kanya. This is
a major discussion in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So the first opinion says it's
not קניא. kanya. So when you take that money of your winnings,
then you're a גזלן. gazlan. Now you're not an out and out
גזלן, gazlan, the guy's giving it to you of his free will,
but technically you're a גזלן gazlan because he really doesn't owe you
that money, he's giving it to you because he thinks he owes
you and therefore when you're taking it you are basically taking money
that is not yours. So that is, it's not a מתנה matana
because he's only giving it to you because he thinks he owes
it to you. So that's the first opinion that says anybody who
does that is פסול לעדות pasul le'edut because essentially they wind up
taking money that's not theirs.
Whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, technically you actually it is
a binding contract, you are entitled to the money. And therefore the
only problem with these people is not that they're גזלנים, gazlanim, the
only problem is that they are not עוסק ביישובו של עולם. osek
beyishuvo shel olam. They don't really spend their time in, you know,
doing sort of serious types of, you know, of earning their own
money. You know, they're and therefore because they don't invest seriously in
a job and in earning money, if this is their only profession,
then they don't appreciate the value of money. And therefore they are
more easily, you know, to be suspected. If you take a look
at רש"י Rashi
four lines down, בזמן שאין לו אומנות אלא היא, bizman she'ein lo
umnut ella hi, רש"י Rashi says דקסבר רבי יהודה אסמכתא שהוא נסמך
על דעתו שהוא ינצחנו ועל אותו אסמכתא הוא מתנה קניא, de'kasvar Rabbi
Yehuda asmachta shehu nismach al da'ato shehu yenatzechenu ve'al oto asmachta hu
matneh kanya, that that bet that you assume that you'll win, that
actually is binding. And even if you don't win, you really are
willing to pay. ולאו גזלנים נינהו, velav gazlanim ninhu, they're not a
גזלן. gazlan. So why are they פסול? pasul? ופסולי נינהו לפי שאין
עוסקין ביישובו של עולם. upsuluy ninhu lefi she'ein oskim beyishuvo shel olam.
They're not doing anything that's beneficial to society. Okay, they're spending their
whole day gambling, playing video games, whatever they're doing, they're not doing
anything that's helping society. And therefore what? If this is their, if
they have no real other profession, it's not that they gamble at
night and at the weekends, this is the only thing they do.
וכיון דאין מכירין בקיאם בטורח וצער בני אדם. vekivan de'ein makkirim beki'am
betorach vetza'ar benei adam.
They don't understand what it really means to go out and get
a job in the real world and what the effort that's required
and the challenges that it requires. אינם חסים על חבריהם מלהפסידם ממון.
einam hasim al havreihem le'hafsidam mammon. Then they don't really value, you
know, money. And therefore they're not, they don't care so much about
people's loss of money and therefore they're not going to, you know,
they're not going to take the testifying falsely
seriously because it doesn't, it doesn't have the weight for them, the
implications of what it means to be, well, that's a good question.
But anyway, but here the context is דיני ממונות. dinei mammonot. So
you know, it's interesting, what about a guy that spends his whole
time, you know, learning and day-to-day by ישיבה? Yeshiva? What about a
guy that spends his whole time sitting, you know, in his home
and like doing day trading? If you actually make money, a lot
of people lose money that way. But anyway,
you know, so you know, never done an honest day's work in
their life, they're never doing anything in terms of the benefit, larger
benefit of, you know, society. And it's true, sometimes that means that
they don't really appreciate, you know, what hard-earned money, the significance of
that. So that's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position and therefore he says
that it's only if this is their only profession. So the גמרא
Gemara says ותניא לה, vetanya lah,
now how do you know whether he's clarifying or debating? So ותניא
לה בברייתא, vetanya lah bivraita, we taught a ברייתא braita about this:
וחכמים אומרים בין שאין לו אומנות אלא היא בין שיש לו אומנות
שלא היא הרי זה פסול. vechachamim omrim bein she'ein lo umnut ella
hi bein sheyesh lo umnut shelo hi harei zeh pasul. Clearly that's
not what everybody agrees to, that the חכמים chachamim say whether it's
your only profession or even if it's not your only profession, you're
invalid because you're a גזלן. gazlan. So you see that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is not clarifying, he's debating. גמרא Gemara says no, ההיא
דרבי יהודה אמר רבי טרפון היא. hahi deRabbi Yehuda amar Rabbi Tarfon
hi. That חכמים chachamim that say it doesn't matter, that you're always
פסול, pasul, is a different חכמים chachamim of the משנה. Mishna. In
the משנה Mishna it was that it said that they're invalid, that
was just a case of that that was your only profession and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was clarifying and there was not a debate
going on in the משנה. Mishna. There is another opinion out there
that says even if it's not your only profession and that's the
opinion of interestingly רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda again but in the name
of רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. דתניא detanya we have in a ברייתא:
braita: אמר רבי יהודה משום רבי טרפון לעולם אין אחד מהם נזיר.
amar Rabbi Yehuda mishum Rabbi Tarfon le'olam ein echad mehem nazir. Now
it's a very interesting where the גמרא Gemara gets this comparison from.
If two people are sitting on a park bench and somebody walks
in front of them, thank you, and one of them says, "I'm
a נזיר nazir if he's a נזיר," nazir, and the other one
says, "I'm a נזיר nazir if he's not a נזיר." nazir. So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says in the name of רבי טרפון, Rabbi
Tarfon, neither of them are נזיר nazir rather than saying they're both
a נזיר nazir מספק misafek or let's find out what that guy
was and we'll figure out who was the נזיר. nazir. He says
neither of them were a
נזיר nazir why? אין אחד מהם נזיר. ein echad mehem nazir. Because
נזירות nezirus is only for הפלאה, hafala'ah, is the act of articulating,
a verbal act that creates a halachic state, turning yourself into a
נזיר, nazir, sanctifying sanctifying an object, etc. And what this means is
that that act is only valid if it is explicit, if it's
not sort of, you know,
dependent on, if you look at Rashi, להפלאה שהיא נדור מפורש על
הודאי ולא על הצד ספק, lehafala'ah shehi nidor meforash al havada'i velo
al hatzad safeik, it has to be like absolute, it can't be,
you know, in doubt whether it really is going to be effective
or not. Now okay, the language of אלא להפלאה, ela lehafala'ah, הפלאה
hafala'ah is the technical name of the category of these verbal acts
that create a change of state, so you might say that's a
limited requirement by acts of הפלאה hafala'ah that you have to, you
can't be in doubt, you have to certainly want it to take
effect. But the גמרא Gemara says, makes a very broad analogy, אלמא
כיון דמספקא ליה אי נזיר אי לאו נזיר הוא לא משעביד נפשיה,
alma keivan demasfka lei i nazir i lav nazir hu lo meshabeid
nafsheih, you see that the logic is that if you're uncertain whether
you're really going to be a נזיר nazir or not then deep
down we don't say you really have committed to doing it. And
if that's true by this act of becoming a נזיר, nazir, interestingly
we're going to jump to a completely different category and say הכא
נמי כיון דלא ידעי אי קני אי לא קני לא גמר ומקני.
hacha nami keivan dila yadi i kani i lo kani lo gamar
umakni. Since you don't know if you actually are going to take
possession or not, actually here it doesn't mean take possession, it means
if you're going to win or not, you're not really committing yourself
to pay if you're going to lose because you don't really believe
you're going to lose and you're not really certain and it's not
deep down a real commitment. So the גמרא Gemara turns this issue
about הפלאה hafala'ah and נזיר nazir into a question of גמר דעת,
gemar da'as, how much do we say you really are committing, which
can be applied across many categories rather than making it a technical
requirement in the laws of נזיר, nazir, in the laws of הקדש.
hekdeish. Okay, so the answer therefore is yes, there are opinions out
there that say that אסמכתא לא קניא asmachta lo kanya and that
this person would be פסול pasul even if it's only a side
gig, but that's not in the משנה. Mishnah. And the משנה, Mishnah,
when רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says this is only if it's your
main profession, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is actually clarifying the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. That doesn't mean that there aren't other people elsewhere that
actually disagree, but in the משנה Mishnah he was clarifying, he wasn't
disagreeing. Did you have a question?
I was just going to ask about a lot of Jews have
been big in the gambling industry, casinos.
Right, that's interesting. And actually a lot of תשובות, teshuvos, not just
in the modern period, going back hundreds of years, about Jews that
would gamble. Sometimes I think if I'm remembering correctly,
there were actually cases about that they would even do it sometimes
on שבת. Shabbos. So anyway,
but yeah, so it's an issue. So you know, hopefully if we
rule like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, then it actually then, you know,
at least you're not an automatic גזלן. gazlan. The interesting thing is,
you know, תוספות Tosafos has a whole discussion about even if we
rule that אסמכתא לא קניא, asmachta lo kanya, what are the parameters?
And he goes through different cases, like he says things that are
maybe complete games of chance, like a lottery ticket. He says then
it would be קניא kanya because then it's like you go in
knowing who knows what's going to happen, it's quite possible you're going
to lose and therefore you're prepared to lose the money. Things that
are completely like under your control, and he talks about another גמרא
Gemara that deals with אסמכתא asmachta which isn't gambling but with its
penalty clause. If I don't do A, B, and C, if I
don't basically till your land, I will have to pay you a
hundred thousand dollars. So it's an out of
proportion thing, so you could say it's crazy, I never committed to
it, but it's a penalty clause and it's something that you actually,
it's under your control. So there we might say that אסמכתא asmachta
is קניא. kanya. So if it's completely under your control, even if
it's out of proportion, or if it's completely luck, so in those
cases you are really serious about it. Either you think you're able
to control it or you know going in that, you know, whatever
happens happens. He says it's the middle cases, which are some degree
chance and some degree skill, which like playing I don't know poker
or something like that, where you actually think, like you know, you
really believe in your own skill and you think you're going to
win and therefore you're not really committed to paying if you lose.
So that's the issue he says of the debate of אסמכתא קניא
asmachta kanya or לא קניא. lo kanya. And at the end of
תוספות Tosafos he says an interesting point. He says about making a
bet, he says like this:
What's a גורל? goral? It's a lottery. He
says like
this, ואותם המשחקים באמנה, ve'osam hamesachakim be'amana, those people that bet, like
play, essentially go into a bet, that's what it means. אומר ר"י
דאינו חייב לשלם, omeir r"i de'eino chayav leshaleim, that's not binding. במאי
יקנה, bimei yikneh, because what makes a bet binding? Besides the question
of your גמר דעת, gemar da'as, for anything to be binding there
has to be a מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, there has to be
some act that finalizes it. So he says דלמאן דאמר אסמכתא היא
לא קניא אפילו בקנין. dileman de'amar asmachta hi lo kanya afilu bekinyan.
and at a בית דין חשוב be-veit din chashuv דכמיכה דבן אדם
de-chamicha de-ven adam even if אסמכתא, asmachta, if אסמכתא asmachta is לא
קניא lo kaniya it'll never work. ולמאן דאמר לאו אסמכתא היא, ule-man
de-amar lav asmachta hi, even if you say it's not an אסמכתא
asmachta or you say אסמכתא קניא, asmachta kaniya, היכי קני בדברים בלא
קנין בשביל
שנוצח חברו? heichi kani bidevarim belo kinyan bishvil shenotzeach chaveiro?
So just because you make a verbal bet, there is no מעשה
קנין ma'aseh kinyan to make it binding. So Tosfos actually says for
it to be halakhically binding you need a, first of all it
shows people were making bets. But anyway you need an act and
it has to deal with the issues of אסמכתא קניא asmachta kaniya
or not. Either we פסקן pasken אסמכתא קניא asmachta kaniya or if
we פסקן pasken אסמכתא לא קניא, asmachta lo kaniya, maybe there are
cases at both extremes which are not considered to be אסמכתא. asmachta.
So anyway out of an interesting side
note,
many years ago, decades ago, anyway when I was, I heard a
שיעור shiur from Rav Lichtenstein about the question about buying a lottery
ticket and whether it's an אסמכתא. asmachta. So he spent a whole
hour going through all the different שיטות shittos about אסמכתא קניא asmachta
kaniya or לא קניא lo kaniya and how do we פסקן? pasken?
What's defined as אסמכתא? asmachta? And then he says at the end,
he says, but none of this is relevant, because he says you're
not making a bet, you're buying something. You're buying a ticket. So
it's like you go into a store, you buy an apple, you
buy a ticket. So he says if it happens
that the ticket wins, fine, but you're not. So I
said after to myself, I don't get it. The problem about
אסמכתא קניא asmachta kaniya is if you win, for the other guy,
if you lose the other guy is the גזלן, gazlan, if you
win, then the problem is you're the גזלן. gazlan. So I said,
who cares if you're buying the ticket at the time? If you
win, which he of course never considered the possibility,
if you win, then they don't really owe you the money, then
you're taking the money that at that moment they're giving you money
that they're only giving you because of a promise essentially of the
rules of the game, what's really binding then. So anyway he said,
I think they want to give you the money because that way
people buy the tickets. Anyway it was a whole conversation. So but
that's an interesting question. Also you could have just said like this
Tosfos pointed, if it's complete luck. But anyway so that's an interesting
discussion about אסמכתא קניא. asmachta kaniya. With that we end this פרק,
perek, הדרן עלך חלון, Hadran alach Chalon, and we begin a new
one. And again the last point here being that basically עירוב תחומין
eiruv techumin is a trade-off, so the person has to be a
much more active participant in the making of עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin.
עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros is all to the person's benefit. So certainly
if you're using your food for the person, it doesn't matter whether
they've bought into it or not. Whereas if you're using their food,
that was more of an issue, can you do it for them
even using their food and even walking into their house and taking
their
food, or if you have access to their food, are you allowed
to do that since it's basically all a benefit. Okay, now we
get back since we've been discussing the actual act of making עירוב
חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, we now go back to the act of doing
עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumin. כיצד משתתפין בתחומין? keitzad mishtatfin bitechumin?
How do we make an עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumin, since we just
discussed how do we make an עירוב חצרות? eiruv chatzeiros? So מניח
את החבית, maniach et hachavit, you take a barrel, a barrel filled
with whatever food products it's filled with. ואומר הרי זה לכל בני
עירי. ve-omer harei zeh le-chol benei iri. עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin can
be out of any food. It's only the עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros
that has to be out of bread. ואומר הרי זה לכל בני
עירי. ve-omer harei zeh le-chol benei iri. This is for all the
people of my city. Now we just learned that it's not always
a good thing. So you say on the following condition: לכל מי
שילך לבית האבל, le-chol mi she-yeilech le-veit ha-avel,
anybody who needs to go to a שבעה shiva house, או לבית
המשתה, o le-veit ha-mishteh,
because you can be מנחם אבלים menachem aveilim on
שבת, Shabbat, או לבית
המשתה, o le-veit ha-mishteh, or going to a
שבע ברכות sheva brachot in the next city. וכל שקיבל עליו מבעוד
יום מותר. ve-chol she-kibel alav mi-be'od yom mutar.
Anybody who before שבת Shabbat began said, yeah I want to actually
do that, I want to go to that next city, and therefore
then fine, then some of that food is yours and therefore you've
made an עירוב eiruv and you're entitled to go to the next
city. משתחשך, mishetachshach, if you decided after it became dark, אסור. assur.
שאין מערבין משתחשך, she-ein me'arvin mishetachshach, an עירוב eiruv has to take
effect from the previous day. So here on the one hand somebody
is doing it for me, on the other hand it's only under
the circumstance where I am buying in. So my buying, because and
this is the idea, I can't just סתם stam do it for
somebody else because it's a trade-off for them. You gain in one
direction, you lose in another. So I'm only doing it for people
who say they want to be a part of it. The other
interesting thing though is what don't we have here that we had
by the עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, when I was taking bread or
whatever for everybody in the חצר? chatzer?
לא עשינן סעודות הכא
lo
asinan
seudos hacha over here.
Okay, well there's a question of quantity which we'll get to. But
also in terms of the act, what am I not doing here?
I'm not giving it to a third party to take possession for
them. I'm not מזכה. mezakeh. And that's why the גמרא Gemara said
that the simple sense, which was Shmuel's position, is you have to
be מזכה mezakeh by עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, you don't have to
be מזכה mezakeh by עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumin, which is quite fascinating.
As long as I am putting food there for you and you
want to be part of that, even if it's not
your
food. that it sounds like at least from the משנה Mishna *Mishna*
that the idea of מזכה *mezakeh* is not needed by עירוב תחומין
Eruv Techumin *Eruv Techumim*.
Yes, Charlie? And just on the ArtScroll, the statement that they have
there doesn't mention anything about anybody else owning or must maintain.
No, no, no, you don't have to do it this way. It's
funny that it says כיצד *keitzad* and it gives a special case,
but that's the way the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* is. Like the normal
case is boring, so it wanted to start with an interesting case.
And it is interesting. Number one, it talks about making a general
statement that people buy into and at the time you made the
statement you didn't know who was going to be included. And it
also tells the idea about this issue that you don't have to
be מזכה *mezakeh* for them. It's enough to put down food for
them even though it's not their food. Yes.
But it's a very odd contrast between being so דקדוק *dikduk* about
gambling and or stealing from somebody, right, but permitting you to go
into somebody's house even against their will and steal their food for
your purposes to make a...
Right, well, okay, so that is true but at the time I
think I mentioned although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that, תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafot* at least tries to limit that statement. That was one statement
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. A lot of the statements of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* were about having to be with the person's דעת
da'at *da'at* or at least it was less to that degree. It
was כופין
אותו
*kofin oso*. There was a כופין *kofin*. It was said בעל כורחו
*bal korcho*. Right, בעל כורחו *bal korcho*. Right, it's true. It's a
very... it's a good point. I mean תוספות *Tosafot* tries to tone
it down by saying it was talking about that his wife gave
it for him. But you're right, it is a... it definitely is
an interesting contrast especially because in this case of the gambling the
person is doing it willingly and we're just... right, right.
That's a good point, as opposed to the other where we are,
right, at least in the simple sense of that one statement, sounds
like you actually are forcibly taking the food for his participation. That's
a good point.
Yes, rabbi, along the same line. So you put down this עירוב
תחומין eruv techumim *Eruv Techumim* and you have in mind that it's
for everybody, whether you know them or not, whether...
Only if they agree to it because it's עירוב תחומין eruv techumim.
*Eruv Techumim*. That's the whole point. Since it's an עירוב Eruv? תחומין
*Eruv Techumim* they lose on one side what they gain on the
other, you can't do it for them unless they agree to it.
Okay,
so what if somebody after שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, after the תחומין *techumim*
was set, says, 'Oh, I just found out there's a שבעה *shiva*
house, I want to go', even though they started שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*...
Well, that's what the משנה Mishna *Mishna* says. They have to have
made the decision before it got dark. Okay. So that's what the
משנה mishnah. *Mishna* says. So we'll see about that in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, right. Exactly, and it has to happen before dark.
Oh, but what should I find out that there was a need...
All right, we'll see. אמר רב יוסף אין מערבין אלא לדבר מצוה
*Amar Rav Yosef Ein mearvin ela lidvar mitzvah*. So רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef* says an עירוב Eruv. תחומין *Eruv Techumim*, and we've mentioned this
a number of times that when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discusses עירוב
Eruv תחומין *Eruv Techumim* it assumes that it's being done for a
דבר מצוה *dvar mitzvah*. So that's the only time that the rabbis
allowed it, which is pretty funny. You mean to do it for
something else? No, for yourself. מאי קא משמע לן *Mai ka mashma
lan*? What does this teaching us? תנינא *Tanina*, it's in the משנה
mishnah *Mishna*. לחכם שילך לבית האבל או לבית המשתה *Lachacham sheyeilech lveit
ha'aveil o lveit hamishteh*. It makes it very clear that the examples
it gave were מצוה *mitzvah* examples. ניחום אבלים, משמח חתן וכלה *Nichum
aveilim, mesameach chasan v'kallah*. No, מהו דתימא אורחא דמילתא קתני *Mahu d'teima
orcha d'milsa katani*. I might have thought that this was just common
examples, but it didn't mean to limit it to those cases. קא
משמע לן *Ka mashma lan* that it has to be לדבר מצוה
*lidvar mitzvah*. And that's very fascinating. It's almost like this aside
statement, it has to be לדבר מצוה *lidvar mitzvah*, made an עירוב
Eruv. *Eruv* from the משנה *Mishna*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* pretty
consistently assumes that. If you remember when it's talking about it like,
why can you put, according to רבי *Rebbi*, can you put an
עירוב Eruv *Eruv* in a tree even though it's מוקצה *muktzah*, even
though you can't use a tree because it's בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*,
there's no דרבנן *derabanan* בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*, but then that gets
qualified, well maybe it's only because it's לדבר מצוה *lidvar mitzvah*. This
general assumption that you're always doing it לדבר מצוה *lidvar mitzvah*, although
in the משניות mishnayos *Mishnayot* I don't think you get that strong
assumption, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of reads that in and
constantly assumes that עירוב Eruv תחומין *Eruv Techumim* is לדבר מצוה *lidvar
mitzvah*. And that's quite interesting why עירוב Eruv תחומין *Eruv Techumim* is
different that way than עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros *Eruv Chatzerot*. If anything,
it could be because עירוב Eruv תחומין *Eruv Techumim* is going more
against like even if it's דרבנן *derabanan*, the פסוק *pasuk* like שבו
איש תחתיו *shvu ish tachtav* and so on, there's more of a
pushing up against that פסוק *pasuk*. So therefore maybe חז"ל *Chazal* only
allowed it in the cases of the דבר מצוה *dvar mitzvah*. You
could also say that the whole idea of עירוב Eruv תחומין *Eruv
Techumim* as we've discussed before, of עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros *Eruv Chatzerot*
is sort of essentially bringing people together and creating a coherent שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* community. So that's like an intrinsic good in itself, so
that's something we basically always want people to do, whereas the עירוב
Eruv תחומין *Eruv Techumim* is really in a sense almost like leaving
the community. I mean you're going to leave to somewhere else, but
you're actually going away. So it is interesting that they have this
requirement, again, not explicit in the משנה *Mishna*, of לדבר מצוה *lidvar
mitzvah*, which is not the requirement by עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros *Eruv
Chatzerot*. Yes.
But even in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, don't we have cases that
this rabbi and that rabbi were walking and one was מכיר *makir*
the אילן *ilan* and the other wasn't and I didn't get the
sense necessarily that was for דבר מצוה *dvar mitzvah* unless it was
to get home in time for שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*.
Well, getting home for time for שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is a דבר
מצוה *dvar mitzvah*. You know, not being stranded in the middle of
the
outside of
the city. So if it's a nice
day and I want to take a walk and the no one's
then they're also saying I can't do that?
No, I don't know. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. וכל שקיבל עליו מבעוד יום, V'chol
she'kibel alav mib'od yom, so you have to have accepted it from
the day before. שמע מינה אין ברירה, Shma mina ein breira,
from this we can infer that why do you have to say
oh yes I want to go to you know use that עירוב?
Eruv Why do you have to decide it from the previous day?
Even if you decided on שבת, Shabbos maybe we should you know,
why should it not work? It must be because of אין ברירה
Ein breira that we don't say retroactively it makes it clear that
I always wanted to go. דאי יש ברירה, De-ee yesh breira, if
we would say יש ברירה, Yesh breira, things are clarified retroactively. תיגלי
מלתא למפרע, Tikli milta l'mafrea,
why do we say it became revealed retroactively דמבעוד יום הוה ניחא
ליה, de-mib'od yom havi nichleh leih, that if you want now obviously
it shows that you always wanted it. Which is so funny because
you know the גמרא Gemara elsewhere and I think we said this
last time we did ברירה Breira makes a distinction between תולה בדעת
עצמו Toleh b'daas atzmo and תולה בדעת אחרים. Toleh b'daas acheirim. Like
I can change my mind you know multiple times in a minute
in a day or whatever. Just 'cause I'm deciding now I want
to go doesn't mean that I always had wanted to go, right?
So even within the יש ברירה Yesh breira if it's about a
question about me making a decision or not, you might say that
at that time I hadn't made that decision then we don't say
retroactively I made that decision at that time you say that I
changed my mind later and I had made a decision later which
I hadn't made before. But the גמרא Gemara says no why don't
we just say and especially as תוספות points out even though there's
a debate do we say יש ברירה Yesh breira or אין ברירה,
Ein breira, by עירובין Eruvin where we're generally so lenient we should
be always we should adopt the most lenient position here about ברירה
Breira and we should say that even if I wind up deciding
שבת Shabbos morning it shows that already Friday night before שבת Shabbos
began I had already wanted to go and therefore I was part
of the עירוב. eiruv So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi says you're right and
therefore הודיעו ולא הודיעו קתני. Hodiu v'lo hodiu katanai. The משנה should
not be read that if I was if I was accepted upon
myself or not, he ממש Mamaish changes the text of the משנה,
that I have to accept it upon myself before שבת Shabbos begins.
He just says I have to be informed before שבת Shabbos, begins.
If I was informed before שבת Shabbos begins hey if you want
to go to the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos you can join into
the עירוב eiruv and then even if I made up my mind
שבת Shabbos day we'll say that oh retroactively it shows that I
was part of it. But if I wasn't informed ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos then I can't have retroactively been part of it right because
there was no there was no opportunity to buy in but if
I was given the opportunity to buy in and I was informed
then even if I make my decision after שבת Shabbos, begins. Not
at all פשט Pshat of the משנה but the גמרא Gemara accepts
that we're going to be lenient and we're going to say יש
ברירה Yesh breira and it's enough that I was informed beforehand even
if I make up my mind later.
What about all these things about the חכם, Chacham, that's the חכם
Chacham coming here and
you know the מזרח Mizrach חכם Chacham goes there? Right there was
also יש ברירה. Yesh breira. So אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
that's what we פסקן Pasken though. אמר רב אשי קטן בן שש,
Amar Rav Ashi katan ben sheish, now we get into another interesting
discussion about say we discussed before like minors and so on here
you know who's the same domain different domain same here we get
a similar issue. אמר רב אשי קטן בן שש יוצא בעירוב אמו.
Amar Rav Ashi katan ben sheish yotzei b'eruv imo. If you have
a minor up to the age of six maybe including the even
even the age of six he goes he's included with his mother's
עירוב. eiruv Meaning until now we've been discussing and we're about to
discuss can I make an עירוב eiruv for somebody without informing them?
Okay? Now again we said by עירוב חצירות Eruv Hatzeiros generally yes,
I'm sorry by עירוב חצירות Eruv Hatzeiros generally yes but עירוב eiruv
תחומין generally no but maybe if this person is under my control
like my kids maybe I can make an עירוב eiruv for them
without informing them even though for normal person I couldn't do it.
That's one issue. Here the question is I'm not making an עירוב
eiruv for my kid I really only made an עירוב eruv. for
me. The mother made an עירוב eruv just for herself but her
kid is considered a part of herself. So it's not like she
made it for he put down extra food for the kid she
just put it down for herself but he's saying
until a kid up to the age of six is considered together
with his mother and therefore it's the same עירוב eruv. with his
mother. So the גמרא Gemara says מיתבי, Meisvei, I'll ask you on
this
קטן שצריך לאמו יוצא בעירוב אמו. Katan she-tzarich l'imo yotzei b'eruv imo.
If a minor still needs his mother then he is together with
his mother whatever עירוב eruv works for his mother works for
him. ושאינו צריך לאמו אין יוצא בעירוב אמו. U-she-ein tzarich l'imo ein
yotzei b'eruv imo. Okay so what is that maybe I would say
six years old is still צריך לאמו? Tzarich l'imo? No I'll show
you not that way. ותנן נמי גבי סוכה כי האי גוונא V'tenan
nami gabei sukkah ki hai gavna because we have a similar distinction
by
סוכה. Sukkah. קטן שאינו צריך לאמו חייב בסוכה. Katan she-ein tzarich l'imo
chayav b'sukkah. If a קטן Katan as once he does no longer
needs his mother then he's חייב Chayav in סוכה Sukkah for חינוך
Chinuch purposes obviously he's not yet an adult but for חינוך Chinuch
purposes once he's no longer dependent on his mother dependent is the
better word here. So ואבינן בה, V'avinan bah, ואיזהו קטן שאינו צריך
לאמו? V'eizu katan she-ein tzarich l'imo? So and over there in סוכה
Sukkah we ask the question what qualifies a minor that's no longer
dependent on his
mother? אמרי דבי רבי ינאי Amri d'bei Rabbi Yannai so the house
of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said כל שנפנה ואין אמו מקנחתו Kol
she-nifneh v'ein imo m'kanachato I love that any anytime he goes to
the bathroom and he doesn't need his mother to wipe him. to
wipe after him. Okay. ריש לקיש אומר, Reish Lakish omer,
which is pretty young. What at what age are kids like that?
Four? Three, four? Okay. So ריש לקיש אומר Reish Lakish omer כל
שניעור ואינו קורא אמא. kol sheneyor v'eino korei ima.
So anytime this kid wakes up and doesn't say Mommy! So the
גמרא Gemara says אמא סלקא דעתך? ima salka daitach? You really?
That's it? Just not saying Mommy? גדולים נמי קרו. gedolim nami karu.
Even a גדול, gadol, I don't think it means I hope it
doesn't mean like a thirty year old, but anyway even if a
kid's Bar Mitzvah or whatever or Bat Mitzvah wakes up in the
middle of the night and says Mommy! So that's do you say
as soon as as long as you're saying Mommy you're still צריך
לאמו? tzarich le'imo? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא, ela eima,
so rather say
כל שניעור משנתו ואינו קורא אמא אמא. kol sheneyor mishinato v'eino korei
ima ima. Doesn't say Mommy, Mommy and keep on saying it until
the mother shows up. So that already is a younger age and
it's actually quite interesting in these few lines the word אימא eima
and אמא ima come up, it's confusing. Anyway, but so okay so
that's the age when he wakes up and doesn't keep on calling
out for his Mommy until she shows up. So how old is
that? וכמה? v'kama? How old is that then when you're out of
that category when you're not צריך לאמו? tzarich le'imo? כבר ארבע כבר
חמש, kebar arba kebar chamesh, about four or five depending on the
kid. So here we said four or five you're no longer in
the category of צריך לאמו tzarich le'imo whereas we said the original
statement in the name of whoever it was was six. Who was
the one that said that? רב אסי. Rav Assi. רב אסי Rav
Assi says six you're still צריך לאמו tzarich le'imo and here we
said four or five you're not צריך לאמו. tzarich le'imo. So what's
the resolution? So look at the עמוד ב. amud bet. So אמר
רבי יהושע בריה דרב אידי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua brei de'Rav Idi, כי
קאמר רב אסי, ki ka'amar Rav Assi, when did רב אסי Rav
Assi say that six is considered
is considered צריך לאמו? tzarich le'imo? כגון דעירב ליה אביו לצפון ואמו
לדרום. kegon de'eirev leih aviv l'tzafon v'imo l'darom. It's not really the
question of together with his mother that he's one with his mother.
It really is people somebody made an עירוב eruv for him. Okay,
but his father made an עירוב eruv in one direction and his
mother made an עירוב eruv in the other direction and the question
is whose עירוב eruv should we assume he wants to be going
with? Would he rather be with his mother or with his father?
That's really the question.
Okay. דאפילו בר שש, d'afilu bar sheish, okay right, דאפילו בר שש
נמי בצוותא דאמיה ניחא ליה d'afilu bar sheish nami betzavta d'imei nicha
leih would rather be with his mother than with his father. Okay,
so it's a very fascinating גמרא. Gemara So it says you're right.
To be one with the mother you have to be three under
four or under five, but to prefer to be with the mother
that's even at the age of six. So if you have two
different עירובין eiruvin made for you and we are trying to assess
which one do we assume is the one that should work for
you or that you would want to work for him, I mean
you're a קטן katan but whatever should or you know that
that we're going to say is the one that's effective, we'll say
it's the one with the person you would want to be with
and therefore it's with the mother. That's his answer, yes.
Just in World War II the kamikaze pilots the Americans could hear
their radio transmissions and what they yelled as they were
bombing their planes was mother.
Really?
They didn't yell long live the emperor, they were screaming mother. Fascinating.
Right.
Shows how how primal that is. Right.
Okay, so would you say things like that by adults? Let's say
you make an עירוב eruv for me one direction and my friend
makes for me in another direction, who where would To
some degree yeah to some degree we try to assess like I
mean the גמרא Gemara had that before about no no the גמרא
Gemara had that that you given you know appointed two שליחים shelichim
to make an עירוב Eruv and they made in opposite directions and
trying to assess where ultimately your דעת da'at is. But that's an
interesting question here. How are we trying to sort of say you
know what would be the דעת of the קטן katan and how
much does that play a role or are we trying or are
we trying to sort of say where do we sort of objectively
say it makes the most sense? Which is a whole interesting question
about the קטן katan once he's חייב בחינוך chayav b'chinuch and he
has to attend to these issues of עירוב Eruv, and care about
them and so on. How much do we treat him as if
he were a בר דעת bar da'at for these types of הלכות?
halachos? It's an interesting question, yes.
And that's what he did in this play Seth because when they
deal with custody they
generally give it to
the mother six and under. Six and under. Above six the boys
go to the father.
Interesting. Well there's actually a גמרא Gemara
that that's based on.
That's הלכה. halacha.
Right, there's a גמרא Gemara that addresses
that directly in the issue of custody, exactly this type of a
discussion, so it's not just by analogy, these issues come up directly
in the גמרא Gemara about custody. Right.
So it's taken very seriously. Right.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this. So that's his answer.
מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this. קטן שצריך לאמו יוצא בעירוב
אמו עד בן שש. katan shetzarich le'imo yotzei b'eiruv imo ad ben
sheish. So here we say no trick answers. It's very clear. It
says until six years old he's together with his mother. So not
four it's not that only up through three which was implied by
saying four and five is independent. So תיובתא דרבי יהושע בר רב
אידי תיובתא. tiyuvta de'Rabbi Yehoshua bar Rav Idi tiyuvta. So that's a
clear contradiction of רבי יהושע בר רב אידי Rabbi Yehoshua bar Rav
Idi that tried to sort of get out of it by saying
it meant that there were competing עירובים eiruvin and which one does
he more want to go to. Here it makes it clear that
up at least up to maybe up to and including but up
to the age of six it's together with his mother automatically and
it's one. Implied by I think four and five is independent. So
תיובתא דרבי יהושע בר אבא ברב אידי תיובתא. Tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yehoshua bar
Abba bar Rav Idi tiyuvta. So that's a clear contradiction of Rabbi
יהושע בר רב אידי Yehoshua bar Rav Idi that tried to sort
of get out of it by saying it meant that there were
competing עירובים eruvs and which one does he more want to go
to. Here it makes it clear that up at least up to,
maybe up to and including, but up to the age of six,
it's together with his mother automatically and it's one עירוב. Eruv, So
לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב אסי? Leima tehvei tiyuvta de-Rav Assi? Maybe it's
a contradiction of רב אסי Rav Assi because רב אסי Rav Assi
said six and this says up to six. So this means through
five he's with his mother and רב אסי Rav Assi said six.
So אמר לך רב אסי Amar lakh Rav Assi עד ועד בכלל.
ad ve-ad bikhlal. No, where it says until six, it means up
to and including six. So actually רב אסי Rav Assi would say
this ברייתא braita supports me. You were telling me, "Oh, we say
four five is independent, how could I say six?" I got this
ברייתא. braita. This ברייתא braita says six. So I'll read the ברייתא
braita not up to six, but up to and including six. So
now we have a ברייתא braita and רב אסי Rav Assi that
says up through six and including six, it's considered to be dependent
on his mother. So now how about what we said about סוכה,
Sukkah, that four or five is independent? Is this contradicting that? לימא
תיהוי תיובתא דרבי ינאי Leima tehvei tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yannai maybe it's a
contradiction of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai that says four or five is
already independent and here we're saying six is dependent. So ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish, so the גמרא Gemara says no, לא קשיא. lo kashya.
הא דאיתא אבוהי במתא הא דליתא אבוהי במתא. Ha de-ita avuhi be-mata
ha de-leita avuhi be-mata. Again, very interesting in terms of the psychology
and the dynamics. Is his father around or not? What does this
mean? So if you look, so רש"י Rashi says, he says that
if the kid is being, I'll read the רש"י, Rashi, הא דאיתא
אבוהי במתא, Ha de-ita avuhi be-mata, it's about 20 lines down the
narrow lines, he says שהתינוק נכנס ויוצא עם אמו לא קרי ליה
צריך לאמו מבן ארבע ולמעלה. She-ha-tinok nikhnas ve-yotzei im imo lo kari
lei tzarikh le-imo mi-ben arba u-lemala. If the father, it shows the
importance of, right, of the issue about single parent families and the
importance of about having a father around. So he says if
the father is, you know, is not like, you know, overseas and
never at home, but the father is regularly at home, and the
kid spends time with the father and then the child gets more,
becomes more independent at an earlier age, or more independent from the
mother. He, what's, there's a technical term for this, not differentiates, what
is it? Individuates, individuate self at an earlier age. Okay, so whereas
if the father isn't at home and he's always with the mother
and the mother is effectively being a single parent for most of
the time, then he remains much more dependent on the mother and
he doesn't get that sense of independence until the age of at
least the age of six. So quite a fascinating little insight there
about that. So it says most cases if the father's around, four,
five is already independent, and when was the ברייתא braita and רב
יהושע בר רב אידי Rav Yehoshua bar Rav Idi
talking about that you needed to be six to be independent, or
you needed to be bigger than six, seven to be independent, that's
when the father was not around. Okay, so that was quite interesting.
Now we go on, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we talk not
about being one with the mother, one with the parent, but doing
it for the sake of people that are dependent, that are sort
of under your control. מערב אדם על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים ועל
ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים. Me-arev adam al yedei beno u-vito ha-ketanim ve-al
yedei avdo u-shifkhato ha-kenanim.
You can make an עירוב Eruv for your minor children or for
your slaves,
your non-Jewish slaves. So non-Jewish slaves are considered property, and your minor
children, they're totally under your control. So this is not they're so
small that they're considered one with you or one with the mother.
No, but they're still under your control and therefore they don't get
a say in terms of the עירוב. Eruv You get the say
where the עירוב Eruv is. So you can make an עירוב Eruv
for them and eat separate food. It's not your food, it's not
the food that you're using for you, it's a separate עירוב Eruv
for them, but you get to determine for them where they are
going to, where you know, where they're going to be. I just
recently had some
whole, whatever, argument with my son about trying to get him to
do something. "What about free will?" You know, so the basic point
is, well, if you're under בר או בת מצוה, bar or bat
mitzvah, no free will, you do what the parent says. So therefore,
wherever the the person, the father decides, or maybe the mother, it's
not clear, anyway, that would determine for the kid. בין לדעתן בין
שלא לדעתן, Bein le-daatan bein she-lo le-daatan, whether it's with their knowledge,
you know, or not, you determine for them. אבל אינו מערב לא
על ידי עבדו ושפחתו העברים, Aval eino me-arev lo al yedei avdo
u-shifkhato ha-ivrim, you cannot make an עירוב Eruv for your Jewish slaves
because they might work for you but they're not considered your property,
not under your control, ולא על ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים, ve-lo al
yedei beno u-vito ha-gedolim, and not your adult kids, ולא על ידי
אשתו, ve-lo al yedei ishto, and not for your wife, אלא מדעתם.
ela mi-daatam.
These are people that you don't, you don't get to make decisions
for them. They're, they're adults, they're free people, they make their own
decisions. So there, you cannot say I am deciding this is where
my wife's עירוב Eruv, is. She has to agree to it.
"Can he nullify their vows?" "You can nullify your wife's vows."
Okay, so there, yeah, she
can make her own decisions.
Well, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with that. Anyway, the
nullifying vows is in a limited context by where it impacts you
and so on, but yes. תניא אידך. Tanya idakh. We taught another
ברייתא. braita. לא יערב אדם על ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים. Lo ye-arev
adam al yedei beno u-vito ha-gedolim. You cannot make an עירוב eruv
for your adult children, ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו העברים, ve-al yedei avdo
u-shifkhato ha-ivrim, or your male and female Jewish slaves, ולא על ידי
אשתו, ve-lo al yedei ishto, and not for your wife, אלא מדעתם,
ela mi-daatam, only with their awareness. אבל מערב הוא על ידי עבדו
ושפחתו הכנענים, Aval me-arev hu al yedei avdo u-shifkhato ha-kenanim,
you can do it for your non-Jewish slaves, ועל ידי בנו ובתו
הקטנים, ve-al yedei beno u-vito ha-ketanim, and your minor children, בין לדעתן
בין שלא לדעתן, bein le-daatan bein she-lo le-daatan, with or without their
awareness, מפני שידן כידו. mipnei she-yadan ke-yado. Their hand is like his
hand, which basically means, I mean, that's by the slaves, it means
they're your property, but what it basically means is you are in
total, you are in control. So the, basically the same ברייתא. braita.
And וכולן שעירבו, v'chulan she'irvu, but now we have the end which
is a little strange. וכולן שעירבו ועירב עליהן רבן, v'chulan she'irvu v'eirev
aleihen rabban, any of them that made an עירוב eruv and their
master made an עירוב, eruv, יוצאים בשל רבן yotzim b'shel rabban for
them, meaning, not the master's own עירוב, eruv. he made it for
them, so the master's עירוב is the one that dictates. Meaning, if
my minor kid or my slave goes ahead and makes an עירוב
in the east and I make an עירוב for him in the
west, he can say, 'Oh, I already made my own.' Again, it's
the same point. Not only can I make for you without your
buy-in, I can even make for you and override what you did.
I am the only one who decides here, not you. Okay, so
even if they went ahead and made their own עירוב and I
made an עירוב for them, my עירוב is the one that is
-- takes effect. חוץ מן האשה, chootz min ha-isha, with the exception
of the wife, מפני שיכולה למחות, mipnei she-yechola limchot, because she can,
you know, oppose, you know, she can protest, she can make her
own decision. So the גמרא Gemara says, אשה, Isha, the wife, מאי
שנא, mai shna, why only her? Because, you know, what about the
case of the adult kids? What about the case of the Jewish
slaves? Right, all of those we said were their own, you know,
could make their own decision. So why did we say here that
only except for the wife? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, אשה וכל דדמי לה. Isha v'chol d'dami la. We don't
mean just אשה, Isha, we mean the category that included the wife.
Okay, so there are two basic categories. There's the category of slaves
and minor children, which they don't have any say, I do it
and even if they tried to do something, what I do overrides.
And then there's the category of wife and adult kids and so
on where they actually, A, I can't do it without them, and
all the more so B, if they did their own thing and
I tried to do something, their thing takes effect and not my
thing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר מר,
Amar Mar, חוץ מן האשה מפני שיכולה למחות. chootz min ha-isha mipnei
she-yechola limchot. So
I, if my thing does not sort of take effect for my
wife, the one I did for her—not just the one I did
for me—the one I did for her is not what's binding, it's
the one she did for herself because she could oppose. Does this
hold you or not? Like, how does that fit in with --
? Well, we're going to see.
So חוץ מן האשה מפני
שיכולה למחות.
chootz min ha-isha
mipnei she-yechola limchot.
טעמא דמחת, taama d'machat, it sounds like the reason what I did
for her doesn't take effect was because she protested. הא סתמא נפקא
בדברא. ha stama nafka b'davra. What do we assume, similar to the
question before about the kid who mother made for him and father
made for him and which would he rather be? So the גמרא
Gemara is saying, look, I understand that if my adult kids or
my wife or my Jewish slaves, you know, want to do their
own thing, they're entitled. Okay, and but what do I assume? What
do I assume like, as a -- you know, as a default
position? They probably want to do what I am going to do
for them. You know, maybe because we'll all go together as a
family, they generally, you know, sort of see to my decisions about
these types of issues. Do we sort of take the -- even
though they're entitled to make their own decision, do we assume that
as a default they're going to go along with what I said
and that I can do it for them even without informing them?
So it says, it sounds like yes, because it sounds like the
wife has to oppose, actively oppose, for it not to be binding.
הא תני רישא, ha tani reisha, the beginning of the ברייתא Braita
said אלא מדעתם, ela m'daatam, that I can't do it without their
awareness, I need their active agreement, it's not -- I can't just
assume their agreement. מאי לאו דאמרי הן? mai lav d'amri hen? Doesn't
that mean that they actively have to say yes? לא. lo. מאי
אלא מדעתם? mai ela m'daatam? No. What does their awareness mean? דאשתקו,
d'ishtaku, that they haven't said anything. לאפוקי היכא דאמרי לא, l'afukei heicha
d'amri lo, to exclude a case where they actively oppose. So it
would only be an issue if they actively oppose. So the גמרא
Gemara says, how could you say that? והא דכולן שעירבו ועירב עליהן
רבן יוצאים בשל רבן, v'ha d'chulan she'irvu v'eirev aleihen rabban yotzim b'shel
rabban, וסתמא הוא. v'stama hu. It says if they made and I
made, then -- then -- then that's
a case where they didn't say anything. I went ahead and made
and they went ahead and made, they didn't say anything.
וקתני, v'katani,
and
the end of it says חוץ מן האשה, chootz min ha-isha, that
when the wife -- my wife goes ahead and does something, that
what I did is not binding, even though there she didn't actively
oppose. שלא נפיק, shelo nafik, and then they're -- my thing isn't
binding for her. So the answer there is obvious. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, כיון שעירבו, kivan she'irvu, since she made her own עירוב, אין
לך מיחוי גדול מזה, ein lach michui gadol mizeh, there's no better
way of showing that she's not interested in what you're doing. So
the גמרא Gemara interestingly, interestingly, and, you know, Paul, this a little
bit goes back to your point, it -- it comes back to
a more, you know, realistic position in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara right? Because it's not, you know, the idea that the wife
and the children, even the adult children and the slaves or whatever
are totally independent entities and they go off and they make their
own plans and whatever I do, you know, that's a little unrealistic.
Obviously, there's a dynamic there and the father is, you know, generally
in the patriarchal society still the head of the family and mostly
making, you know, the decisions. So the גמרא Gemara interestingly, like, moves
back to that middle and says, fine, you're right. As a default,
what the father will do or what the husband will do or
the master will do will be assumed to be the decision for
the others and he can do it for them, but they are
entitled, they are, bottom line, they are their own people and they
are, you know, they do have their own, you know, they do
have independence to make their own choice and therefore if they actually
actively, implicitly or explicitly -- implicitly say I don't want to be
a part of that, I'm doing my own thing, then they actually
are able to do that. The interesting נפקא מינה nafka mina is
before they're not saying anything, that's because they did like oh you
didn't make it, I have
to do something. What? Doesn't
it make a difference? The גמרא Gemara said that if they made
an עירוב it's only מיחוי, michuy, it's only מיחוי michuy if they
knew you made it. Right? Meaning if they made it after you
made it, then it's a מיחוי, michuy, if they made it before
you made it—no, no, no, no, I totally disagree. It's basically saying
they have indicated their will and that their will has as a,
they specific desires to do something which isn't what you desired. It
doesn't have to be a מיחוי michuy vis-à-vis what you do. It's
a statement that they have expressed what they want to do. And
that's enough. Normally we would assume they want to do what you
want to do, but here they've made it clear what they want
to do. The only thing I think that's unclear in the גמרא
Gemara. is the גמרא says דאשתיקו de'ishtiku they were silent, but silence
suggests that they were informed and they didn't oppose. שתיקה. shtika. What
happens if I went ahead and I put an עירוב there for
my wife, you know, this does happen sometimes, I make plans for
my wife assuming of course she'll agree and then she does not,
and she particularly gets upset because I didn't tell her what I
was doing. So what happens if, would you say this that it's
if I informed and they were silent and then it's like שתיקה
כהודאה shtika ke'hoda'ah or, you know, which is more giving more independence
to the wife and the children that they have to actually be
informed and I only interpret their silence as acquiescence? Or do you
say that even if I don't inform them, we assume that they
will agree to what I am going to do for them? So
that is not so clear in the גמרא but I do think
it's interesting that the גמרא moved back to a more like realistic
position for the time of the גמרא about the assumption, you know,
about the degree of dependence and independence. Okay, now we go on
to the next משנה. This פרק perek in many ways parallels these
משניות mishnayos that of the previous פרק perek in terms of doing
the act of making the עירוב, what is the שיעור shiur of
it? Also the order of the משניות is similar. So again, one
distinction we've seen now is the idea of דבר מצווה, devar mitzvah,
and the other distinction of the idea that it appear, the פשט
pshat of the משנה is you don't have, it can even be
your food for somebody else. You don't have to transfer ownership through
a third party. Even so, you can use one person's food, one
person can use his food for another person's עירוב. Okay now, כמה
הוא שיעורו? kama hu shiuro? What's the שיעור? shiur? מזון שתי סעודות
לכל אחד ואחד mazon shtei seudos lekhol echad ve'echad as distinct from
the עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros where two meals' worth would work for
a million people and everybody just has to give a גרוגרת, grogeret,
a pressed fig, if it's a small amount, but once you hit
two meals it can work for a thousand people, here every person
has to give a larger amount, two meals, and there is no
maximum. Now the idea, the reason for this should be I think
obvious why it's a higher amount, because two points. One is like
we've seen by the דבר מצווה, devar mitzvah, there seems to be
more resistance to trying to, you know, to do the עירוב תחומין
which is about, like I said, getting out of the city rather
than the עירוב חצרות which is coming together, so we make it
a little bit harder. But number two, the whole point of the
עירוב חצרות is about creating that sense of community. It's like we
see in the רמב"ם's Rambam beautiful description, everybody gives some of the
flour, you make the little loaf of bread. So the idea is
is that, you know, it you can talk about a corporate entity,
everybody together even a million people is represented by this loaf of
bread. Here, it's about individuals. You don't leave the town as a
community, right? You leave, you go out of your community as an
individual. So it's very it already starts with this idea of not
having that corporate sense of one amount for everyone, but having an
individual amount. And why a higher amount even at the individual level
of a גרוגרת grogeret versus שתי סעודות? shtei seudos? I think is
connected to this idea of trying to encourage עירוב חצרות and to
a certain degree at least, you know, discourage or not make it
too easy to do the עירוב תחומין.
If it's שתי סעודות shtei seudos for
everybody, how's a חבית chavit working for the whole city? A חבית,
chavit, but maybe you only expect five people to join in, but
you're right, it would be limited to the first number of people
until the amount is used up. Let's say, let's say, you know,
how are they going to know? All right, I don't know, I
don't know. You have a sign-up sheet, I don't know. Right. So
the גמרא says like this, they don't have to eat it. Right,
they don't have to eat it. It's there and that touches. Right.
Exactly, exactly. And even if it gets destroyed as long as it
was there when שבת Shabbos began, it takes effect. Okay, לכל אחד
ואחד, lekhol echad ve'echad, מזונו לחול ולא לשבת, mazono lechol velo leShabbos,
the amount you would eat for a weekday, not for שבת, the
two meals, two weekday meals. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי יהודה אומר לשבת ולא לחול,
Rabbi Yehudah omer leShabbos velo lechol, no, שבת-sized meals. וזה וזה מתכוונים
להקל, ve'zeh vezeh mitkavnim lehakel, they both thought they
were trying to be lenient.
The question is do you eat bigger meals on שבת or smaller
meals? So of course our normal answer is bigger meals, right, you
make a big to-do about it, you know, as רש"י Rashi says,
as
the גמרא will say,
as רש"י Rashi already said, you know, they
take, you tend to make it nicer and more tasty so you
have bigger meals. But the argument could be no, you need שלוש
סעודות shalosh seudos for שבת, so therefore you eat less at each
meal, הלוואי, halevai, because of your שלוש סעודות. shalosh seudos. So that's
the debate of whether your שבת meals tend to be bigger or
smaller. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר מכיכר בפונדיון, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
omer mikikar bipundyon, it's the size of a loaf of bread that
would cost a פונדיון, pundyon, which is a small coin, מארבע סאים
בסלע, me'arba se'im besela, when four סאה se'ah go for a סלע.
sela. So that should be self- evident. So basically the way it
works is is that a סלע sela is, I'm not going to
go through the whole math, but a סלע sela is forty-eight פונדיון,
pundyon, okay? Now, that's how much a סלע sela and now a
where was it? And what are you buying with a סלע? sela?
ארבע סאין בסלע arba saeen bisela and four סאה saah is there's
six קב kav to a סאה, saah, so four סאה saah is
twenty-four קב, kav, okay? So for a סלע sela you could buy
four סאה saah of flour. We're ignoring labor costs. The גמרא will
discuss later labor costs. For a סלע sela you could buy four
סאה, saah, which means for forty-eight פונדיון pundyon you could buy twenty-four
קב kav of flour, which means for one פונדיון pundyon how much
could you buy? Math is not so hard. Forty-eight to twenty-four is
a ratio of one to two. So you could buy a half
of a קב, kav, right? Right, one פונדיון pundyon you could buy
a half of a קב kav of flour. So basically a roll,
a loaf of dough going for one פונדיון pundyon when this is
the cost of the flour of a סלע sela for four סאה,
saah, which means that for a פונדיון pundyon you would buy a
loaf of bread made out of a half a קב kav of
flour, ignoring labor costs. What? I don't know, but that's what he
says is the size of שתי סעודות, shtei seudos, okay? So he
says רבי שמעון אומר שתי ידות לכיכר משלוש לקב. Rabbi Shimon omer
shtei yados lakikar mishalosh lekav. So he says no, what we would
be talking about is when you have three כיכר kikar for a
קב, kav, so three loaves equals one קב, kav, which means that
one loaf is a third of a קב, kav, okay? And then
he says שתי ידות, shtei yados, which is two-thirds of that, okay?
So if one loaf is a third of a קב kav but
not even a whole loaf, two-thirds of it. So that is two-ninths
of a קב, kav, okay? So that's what he says in terms
of the size as opposed to a half of a קב, kav,
a much smaller amount he says is what it would be, okay?
That's for שתי סעודות? shtei seudos? That's for שתי סעודות, shtei seudos,
okay? So fine. One minute. One minute. Right. Okay, so now the
גמרא says like this. Okay. חציה לבית המנוגע. chetziya l'veis hamenuga. Now
half of this loaf is now you know we always talk about
כדי אכילת פרס, kedai achilas pras, right? The time it takes to
eat a פרס. pras. פרס pras literally means a half, a half
loaf of bread. So כדי אכילת פרס kedai achilas pras is the
time it takes to eat one meal now of bread. Now what
is that שיעור shiur used for? Generally it's used for if you
eat little little little like by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, when is
it considered to be one act of eating or two acts of
eating, when do they combine? So it's things that you eat in
the time of כדי אכילת פרס kedai achilas pras to combine to
be one act of eating. But now that half of a loaf
is assuming you've got a loaf that is two meals worth. This
is the loaf of bread that we're always talking about when we
say a פרס pras is half a loaf. It's half a loaf
of this loaf, this loaf that is two meals worth. So half
of that loaf is one meal's worth of bread, okay? Now that
one meal's worth, that פרס, pras, is used to measure combining little
eatings for one to be one act of eating, but it's also
used because the תורה Torah says that a person who goes into
a house that has צרעת tzaraas becomes טמא, tamei, and if he
eats in the house of צרעת tzaraas his clothes become טמא. tamei.
And the rabbis say it doesn't literally mean eat in the house,
it means you stay in the house the time it takes to
eat, to eat one meal, which is one meal, which is half
a loaf of a two meal loaf of bread. So it's this
half loaf, this is אכילת פרס. achilas pras. So half of this,
which is the פרס, pras, is what's relevant for בית המנוגע, beis
hamenuga, going into a house with צרעת, tzaraas, וחצי חציה, v'chatzi chatziya,
half of the half, okay, which is a half a פרס, pras,
which is a half a meal, is
לפסול את הגוויה. lifsol es hagviyah. If you eat טמא tamei food
the size of half of a פרס, pras, then even though normally
טמא tamei food does not make a person טמא, tamei, there's a
rabbinic הלכה halacha that it does and eating it, touching it does
not make you טמא tamei but eating it makes you טמא tamei
because of a concern that you'll eat טמא tamei food and then
you'll take a drink of תרומה terumah together with it and the
תרומה terumah will touch the טמא tamei food in your mouth and
so on. So for that it is half of the half, okay?
So basically this is a loaf of bread which is two meals,
a פרס pras means a half which is one meal, okay, and
that's כדי אכילת פרס kedai achilas pras
and a פרס, pras, and a חצי פרס chatzi pras is for
this special הלכה halacha of פסול גוויה, psul gviyah, the פסול psul
of your body when you eat טמא tamei food that amount, that
makes you טמא, tamei, that is a rabbinic.
So taking that top one, the two-ninths of a קב, kav, it's
a really small שיעור shiur then half? Right. Correct. It's like nothing.
I know. Well, it's not half of the two-ninths, it would be
half of the one-third, but yes, it would be quite small. No,
isn't it the two-ninths? No, because it's half of the full loaf.
Okay, that's the way anyway. Okay, so let's see look at the
גמרא. וכמה מזון שתי סעודות? vechama mazon shtei seudos? How much is
the מזון mazon שתי סעודות? shtei seudos? וכמה מזון שתי סעודות *Ve-kama
mazon shtei se'udot*? How much is the two סעודות *se'udot*? I mean
I guess it means according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, because in the end we had these very specific
amounts about רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka*, but in
the beginning it wasn't clear what the two סעודות *se'udot* was. So
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, תרתי ריפתא
דאכרי דאסיא *tarti rifta de-achra'ei asya*, the type like two loaves that
were taken by
cowherds when they would go out into the fields. So they knew
what that meant. מבת בר אבא אמר *Mevat bar Abba amar*, תרתי
ריפתא נהר פפיסא *tarti rifta Naharpapisa*, two loaves that were eaten in
the נהר פפיסא *Nahar Papisa* area, two standard sized rolls, okay, like
I said to you two חלה *challah* rolls. You would know what
I'm talking about when I say two חלה *challah* rolls, okay? So
they knew what they were talking about. אמר ליה רב יוסף לרב
יוסף בריה דרבא *Amar lei Rav Yosef le-Rav Yosef brei de-Rava*, or
some say דרבה *de-Rabba*, אבוך כמאן סבירא ליה *avuch kaman sevira lei*?
Who does he hold like? In this רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* debate? Would שבת *Shabbos* meals or weekday meals? So
he says, כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה *ke-Rabbi Meir sevira lei*. So he
says he holds like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. He says, אנא נמי
כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה *ana nami ke-Rabbi Meir sevira lei*. You know
what? I also hold like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* says the שבת *Shabbos* meals are bigger. דאי כרבי יהודה *de-ee
ke-Rabbi Yehuda*, because if it's like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, קשיא *kashya*,
it would be a difficulty, דאמרי אינשי *de-amri inshi*, what people say,
רווחא לבסימא שכיח *ravcha le-vashima shechi'ach*, which means room for dessert. There's
always room for dessert. So which means that on שבת *Shabbos* things
taste better so people eat bigger meals. So therefore I agree with
his position and therefore if we're going to be lenient, we're going
to raise it by weekday meals and not by שבת *Shabbos* meals.
Okay, we get to wait till tomorrow to finish doing the math
about the סאה *se'ah* and the loaves of bread.